Dry skin [music] can flake, itch, crack,
or even bleed. With the right self-care,
many people can heal dry skin at home.
I'm Dr. Pritha Agarwal, a
board-certified dermatologist. Follow
these tips [music] to treat dry skin and
prevent it in the future.
Take short baths and [music] showers to
hydrate your dry skin. When bathing, be
sure to keep the bathroom door closed.
Use warm [music] water instead of hot
and limit your time in the water to 5 to
10 minutes. After your shower or bath,
gently [music] pat your skin dry. Within
a few minutes of drying off, apply
moisturizer [music] to your skin.
Moisturizers work by trapping existing
moisture in your skin. Ointments and
creams are more effective and [music]
less irritating than lotions. To relieve
dry hands, carry a non-greasy hand cream
with you and apply it after each [music]
hand wash. Wear lip balm or apply
petroleum jelly to your lips. If your
lips sting or tingle after you apply a
lip balm, switch to one that does
[music] not cause this reaction. Only
use gentle fragrance-free skincare
products. Products with fragrance or
alcohol can be harsh for dry, sensitive
[music] skin. If you see the word
unscented rather than fragrance-free,
the product can contain chemicals that
neutralize [music] or hide the odors of
other ingredients. These chemicals can
irritate dry skin. To reduce [music] dry
raw skin on your hands, wear gloves when
you go outside in the winter. You should
also wear gloves before you [music]
perform tasks that get your hands wet,
like washing dishes, and before you get
chemicals, greases, and other substances
[music] like cleaning solutions on your
hands. Choose non-erritating clothes and
[music] laundry detergent. Wear soft
fabric like cotton or silk under wool or
other rough clothing. Use laundry
[music] detergent labeled
hypoallergenic.
Avoid sitting close to fireplaces
[music] or other heat sources. Doing so
can dry out your skin. Opt for a thick
[music] blanket or wear warm layers
instead. Lastly, add moisture to [music]
the air by using a humidifier. Dry skin
also can be a sign of a skin condition
that needs treatment. If these changes
do not bring relief, partner with a
board-certified dermatologist for
treatment.